Hey, welcome to Brandon Sanderson's
writing science fiction and fantasy
lecture series. Today we delve into the
history of publishing and what it means
for authors today. This is kind of a
fire hose lecture where I'm just going
to talk at you really fast for a while.
I hope you enjoy it. Hey everybody,
welcome to writing science fiction
fantasy.
Yay.
Um, you have survived until the end.
This is our final uh set of lectures.
This is the publishing industry. This is
a fire hose uh lecture this week and
next week. You can see on the board what
I'm going to be talking about. Whatever
I get don't get through today, we will
get through next week. So, we'll stop
somewhere in the middle here. Uh there's
more to talk about next week that I
didn't even put on this board. But I'm
thinking we might get to but not include
agents, but who knows? It depends on how
fast various parts of what I'm saying uh
happen. So we are going to talk about uh
the history of the publishing industry,
how it works,
um why it
works works in quotes, um and what
ebooks and audiobooks have done as a
disruption of the industry and how
that's ongoing. All right. So let's talk
about the history of the publishing
industry.
way back when, long ago, you really
couldn't make a living publishing books,
right? Um, once in a while, you know,
you'd have something that would sell
well, but mostly this was something done
by the people who were already well off
and to sell to other people who were
already well off. This started to change
somewhere around Dickens, right? Um, and
then we hit the 1900s. People started
reading a lot. Children couldn't work
anymore. Schooling happened. Um, and the
world started to change in regards to
entertainment. Uh the first kind of big
important thing for you as science
fiction fantasy writers to be aware of
is kind of the p the paperback, hardback
and uh magazine divide that happened
during what we call the golden age of
science
fiction. Back then science fiction
mostly was considered a kind of pulp
lowbrow genre. When I say science
fiction I mean science fiction, fantasy
and horror. uh to a lesser extent
detective um as well. These were
published in serial form in um magazines
and things and serious literature was
published by hardcover publishers. These
are the holdovers from the 1800s that
were prestige publishers that kind of
had the same sort of air of these are
wellto-do individuals publishing for
other wellto-do individuals. This still
has ramifications in our current
environment. If you ask yourself
sometimes about the divide between
popular fiction and uh literary fiction,
it started here. Um what the masses were
reading, they would pay pennies for in
magazines in disposable form. For a long
time, that's where science fiction
happened. Um it was done as juveniles.
It was done in the uh the cereals and
things like this. And then something
happened. The people who had grown up
reading
those started to want more mature
fiction that also had some of the same
imagination and some some of the same
wonder that they had enjoyed as young
people. And indeed somebody came along
named J.R. Tolken. And J.R. Tolken
published Lord of the
Rings. Lord of the Rings really did
change the publishing world. Um Lord of
the Rings came out and then people had
grown up reading science fiction and
fantasy as young people and they were
maturing and the same thing happened in
science fiction fantasy that would
happen in film in the 70s. In the 70s,
you had younger people, younger
directors who had grown up watching kind
of this sort of more exploitation slashh
horror slash u kind of lowbrow as they
would call it monster movies, gangster
movies um usually done as serals like
before other movies and things like that
or or alien you know things. And
suddenly you had Spielberg um and you
had Lucas and you had Scorsesei make
films for mature
audiences using those same sort of ideas
they'd loved when they were young. And
so suddenly you end up with these great
blockbusters that combine these
fantastical ideas, gangster movies,
aliens, um, science fiction, and then
aging them up and creating something
more kind of for an older audience. And
this began the blockbuster era of film.
Um, and it's no coincidence that we have
Jaws and we have um The Godfather and we
have Star Wars and we have um we have ET
and all of these things coming out.
Again, older audience, you know, ET is
still targeted younger. Um, Star Wars is
still would be considered somewhere in
that YA to to new adult age, but the
idea is taking serious film making
techniques and applying them to what had
been
beov. Well, Tolken was ahead of that.
Tolken was uh a fan of fairy stories.
And what he did is he took some of these
things that had usually been mythology
or told for children and he made a
serious adult epic out of it. And the
industry had no idea what to do with
this. Science fiction fans did. They had
already been reading the golden age
science fiction authors that were
begrudgingly published by the
publishers. Your Heinlines, your
azimovs, your Jack Vances. Uh he's
silver, right? He's Scar's favorite. Um
Jack Vance, the father of modern uh
rule-based fantasy uh magic systems. Um
they had been we'd been reading all
these things. I say we I wasn't even
born yet. Um and I'm old, right? So this
is a long time ago. Um they had been
reading all these things and driving
them from the serals into paperback
publishing. Back then hardcover
publishers and paperback publishers were
separate separate companies. You had
your snoody highbrow hardcover
publisher, usually named after some
snoody highbrow hardcover person. If you
look on the spine of a book and it has
someone's name who sounds highbrow, they
probably were a dude who started a
publishing company in the 50s or before
to publish highbrow fiction. H Hotton
Mifflin, right? I guess they're mostly
textbooks now, but you know, all of
these people.
Um, science fiction was seen as a
paperback genre by then, but there were
places that were growing up to publish
it. Tolken drove science fiction into
being
profitable, really profitable. People
saw what was happening as mass audience
adoption. And I say Tolken, I mean
everyone during the silver age there.
Tolken and McAffrey um and all and
Ursula and all these people who are
publishing in the 60s that were doing
serious science fiction. Um, and being
serious, I mean using serious literary
techniques. They were writing them out
of a place of passion and skill. Um, not
that you weren't getting that in the
pulps. There's a lot of great stuff in
the pulpes, but it was, you know, it was
different when you grow up reading it
and you grew up writing it. Now, you can
understand a lot about the science
fiction and fantasy publishing industry
from the fact that at large publishing
ignored us until we started making
money. Because of that, a lot of science
fiction publishing was grassroots. A lot
of the publishers of science fiction
fantasy grew up out of people writing it
and going to conventions, figuring it
out on their own, and then starting
little publishing companies because the
big publishers weren't
interested. And so there was a very kind
of communal feel to science fiction
fantasy in those days, overlapping a lot
with the political movements that were
happening at the time and all this
stuff. And it's all muddled together.
Um, because of this, science fiction
both was a very kind of it was a place
where you could be a nobody and sell a
book, but it was also a place where um
it could feel like a club that you
weren't part of, right? If you didn't go
to all the conventions, cuz all these
people got together and started
conventions to yell about who their
favorite Star Trek captain was. Um,
right? I'm joking because there was only
one back then. Uh, but you know, um, you
know, they they got together so they
could publish their Spock and Kirk
Slashfic and talk about it. That's real,
by the way. Uh, back in the 60s, uh, the
early Fanzines. Um, that's the one of
the origins of fanfiction.
Um, they got together to talk about
their favorite episodes of Star Trek.
And also a lot of writers who are
aspiring writers are going there and
there's famous stories. Um I heard this
one at the very first science fiction
convention I went to about how there was
somebody who got finally got published
and he's like I'm too big for the
conventions now. Uh he was walking
around and he went by the fzine which
fanzines were they were publishing their
own magazines where they would print
them on their printers dot matrix
printers or whatnot and staple them
together. And the person, they're like,
"Hey, come make us help us make
Avengers." And he's like, "I'm a serious
science fiction writer now. I don't do
this." And then Azimov's head pops out
of a door and says, "I need more of page
53 uh to staple in." Um, that's a story
that goes around. I don't know if it's
apocryphal or not, but I was told it at
my first convention. Um, this this was
the
community. Science fiction and fantasy
started making money.
books for the uh the average for the
average person started making money
right around the same time that films
blockbuster films happened. We're
talking the 70s. Tolken preaged this uh
a little bit. The 70s is where it really
took off. All the publishers are like,
"So those science fiction nerds, they
like to buy
stuff. They're all in tech
industries. They have money.
maybe we should be making books for
them. And this coincided with some big
shifts in the publishing industry that
you can watch through the the the
history of kind of just all retail. The
hardcover publishers started realizing
the paperback publishers were making as
much or more money than them. So they
started buying them. Suddenly you have a
hardcover publisher that would print the
paperback, would do the hard coverver
and then release the paperback. In the
past, you had this big prestigious
hardcover publisher, and then the
paperback publisher could do their
science fiction stuff, but occasionally
you would dain to let them have the soft
cover rights for your very important
book that you would eventually release
in soft cover that other people could
then read. I'm exaggerating this, but
you you get the idea. They started
buying up each other. Giant
conglomerates started buying up those
publishers, right? And so suddenly you
have consolidation happening. Um, and
you have giant publishers happening
because this stuff is actually making
money. Our first best sellers in science
fiction and fantasy appear in the
early8s. Before then, nothing that I've
been able to see has charted. Even
Tolken was more of like he sold
regularly, consistently, very well, but
never had weekly spikes to the point
that you could make uh the bestsellers
particularly because it's mostly selling
in paperback. And the bestseller list
didn't count paperbacks. They were only
interested in the hard covers at that
point. And so eventually we start seeing
it happen. And the '9s is the biggest
shift. This is when um and I'm not just
saying this because it's my publisher
and a book series I'm involved in. This
is when the wheel of time is the big
second shift in science fiction fantasy
publishing. Tom Dherty starts tour. So
Tom Dhy is uh is the founder of tour. He
was a publisher. is the paperback
publisher at Gracet and Dunlap. He had
one of he he was one of the people who
just kind of published paperbacks,
right? Um and there are several people
like him. Donald Woolheim was one of
them. Um there's just there's a group of
them that are kind of they're business
people and they see that science fiction
is doing well and Tom goes to the uh
owners of Grass and Dunlap and says, "I
want to try some of the science fiction
stuff." And so they actually bought Ace
Books, a small paperback publisher, and
put Tom in charge of it. He ran Ace
Books uh through the 70s, and made Real
Inroads, and then he started tour
uh to publish hardcover science fiction
and fantasy. He eventually leverages his
company um to McMillan, selling it
basically but with him retaining control
to get money to launch The Wheel of
Time, which is our first major
consistent number one best-selling
hardcover fantasy series in the '90s.
Blows the doors off of everything. Sells
in hard coverver. This is a big deal
because even still selling in hardcover
is where the bulk of the money starts to
come in. Um, hard cover is seen as kind
of the firstr run movie versus the DVD
at this point rather than being the
prestige versus the non-prestige. The
hard cover is where you kind of
frontload with your fans. You produce a
nicer product uh that that has way
better margins and makes you way more
money per copy in order to sell to the
hardcore fans, which means hard covers
suddenly become for the hardcore fans
rather than for the prestige. and the
things that can sell a lot of books in
hardcover suddenly make enough money to
pay for all of the experiments you want
to do and everything else. Um during
this time we continue to consolidate.
One of the big things you need to be
aware of is back in the day there were
hundreds and hundreds thousands of
bookstores around the country all owned
independently. So, you needed to have a
salesforce at your publisher who would
go on the road to visit every one of
those stores with a catalog and get them
to order copies of your books either in
hardcover or paperback. I went on one of
these sales calls during the last years
that they had giant sales forces uh
before ebooks and Amazon destroyed this.
Um, and so I just went on one to see how
it went. It was really interesting. I
went up to Weller Book Works, been
called um uh what do they call it? Uh
Sam Weller Book Company before they
changed their name. Um and just sat as a
fly on the wall as uh McMillan's sales
rep sold the science fiction fantasy
line to this book seller who I love
Weller BookWorks. Science fiction is not
their thing. They just carry it because
uh nerds. Um and so the his name was
Larry Yoder. Fantastic book seller, our
salesman. He's like, "I know your
market. I know exactly, you know, what
you sell. You want this one, this one,
and this one. Uh, this one will sell is
new. It's it's more risky, but you might
find an audience. You maybe don't want
this one, and this one, this one." He
had read every book on that list. He
knew at Weller Book Works what they
sold, and his reputation of being able
to tell them that was really important
to both of them. He knew what their
bookstore would sell. they could trust
him as a salesman to have read the books
and know and to te talk up the debuts
that he thought were worth taking a shot
on. Now part of the reason they could do
this is because in the 40s publishing
almost died because everyone almost died
because you know um well the 30s the 40s
where everyone almost died but met you
know the dust bowl all the stuff back in
the great depression the 30s um so
publishing came up with this idea no one
was taking books by new authors they
came up with this idea they said if you
take the books some of our books by the
new author and they don't sell you can
send them back and we'll give you credit
and you can buy our other books that are
more successful so you never get stuck
holding new authors books that you can't
sell. This started something that still
exists in publishing. It's called the
return um system where any book by the
big publishers is generally returnable.
Meaning a bookstore can send it back for
a full refund credit toward buying
whatever else they want to buy from that
publisher next. Still around, still here
today. So, they're willing to take
chances on new authors because the risk
is very minimal. As long as the
bookstore is going to stay open and the
publisher is going to stay open, they
can send those books back and they can
get some more Stephen King books that
they know will sell. Um, and this is how
they convince author uh people to take
new authors.
So, this is when I broke in at the tail
end of this uh when the salesforce was
still going out. Well, Tom tells this
story about what happened in the late
'9s where um number one, Barnes & Noble
comes in and then borders behind it and
starts closing the little bookshops. If
you want a documentary on this, it's
called You've Got Mail.
Um joking the but man, I'm I'm glad you
guys actually know that movie. That's
that's an old movie now. Um but uh the
big box publisher or uh bookstores
started to put the little bookstores out
of
business. This was bad and
good. It was bad that uh what happened
is it became harder and harder to keep
these giant sales forces going because
there were fewer places to visit. Beyond
that, behind the scenes, the
distributors were also consolidating.
Distributors are the places that would
take the books and sell them to a lot of
the even smaller markets. Usually, uh,
gas stations. They'd have racks of
paperbacks and things like this. And
that was just usually a distributor
bought space, went in, filled it up,
things like this. The distributor
distributors were learning that selling
a hundred
books didn't actually make them as much
as selling 80. You're like, how could
that possibly be? Well, if you have to
go to all these little places and have
all of these cars and all of this
workforce to place those books and all
those little spots and you sell a
hundred, but you can lose half of your
infrastructure and still sell
80. Economics says do that. So they did.
So the bookstore, the book rack started
vanishing from these little places and
the big box stores started taking over
this. This is the beginning of
bestsellers kind of over taking the
industry in a way that I think I've
talked to you a little bit about how the
mid list is started to shrink. Well,
this is because if you're you've got all
this work to sell a 100 books, but you
can sell 80 books with 50% of the work,
the industry says, "Well, maybe we
should do that."
It's a little myopic because a lot of
those 20 books that don't that sell are
to people who wouldn't go to the
bookstores who that raise new
generations of readers or they're pe the
people who are not quite getting served
by the bestsellers might be people um
who otherwise just won't read. They were
reading in a niche genre of something
they really like and the big bestseller
doesn't get them. And over time we lose
readers because they raise fewer readers
and things like this. The bestseller
mentality. Um though I am one of the
biggest bestsellers in the industry is
still worrying to me. But how does this
uh come into play for you guys? Well,
this is what was going on in 2010 when
the biggest shakeup happened since
probably Tolken um said, "Hey, by the
way, nerds will buy books." Uh, and that
is the release of the of Amazon's
Kindle and the ebook
shakeup. We had been bracing ourselves
since Napster. You were almost all too
young to remember how this was. But back
in the day, we had to make
mixtapz. They were
awful. If you wanted to have a specific
song and you couldn't afford the album,
you had to call in to the DJ and then
listen with your tape recorder and try
to capture a copy of the theme song for
Beverly Hills Cop, which they never
played for you because they don't
actually take requests. They just play
the top 40. They just want you to think
they take requests. I'm not bitter. It
was three
hours. Then I listened to that dumb
radio
station. True story.
Um Napster and then iTunes came out,
disrupted the market. We all expected to
happen with ebooks and it didn't. And it
didn't and it didn't and it didn't. And
everyone's like maybe it won't happen.
Maybe people like their print books too
much. Maybe our industry won't be
disrupted and everything will just keep
on going bam. Kindle smash um crash
destroys the market in good ways.
Disrupts the market in good ways. What
does the Kindle do? Um the Kindle proves
that platform is king. People wanted a
easy reading um experience. They wanted
to have a platform. during those days up
on tour.com. I had a short story. Uh
it's defending Alissium. Um it's
actually in promo. It's in uh it's in
tailored reality. It's coming out later
this year. If you haven't read it, it's
also free on tour's website. Um and it
was back then. They're like, "Hey, this
Kindle thing is working. Let's we'll put
it on Kindle for 99 cents. Brandon, you
cool with that?" I'm like, "Yeah, sure."
Then I got a royalty check and it was
like five grand, which doesn't sound
like a lot to you, but it was off of 25%
of 99
cents, right? And for a story that had
been up for free for 4
years, people didn't want to read it for
free. They wanted the convenience of
pushing a button on their
Kindle, right?
like 20,000 people would rather push a
button on their Kindle than go read it
for
free. This is the power of owning the
platform. Okay? And this is what we
learned. Making it easy, making people
want to just push a button and buy. The
gold rush era of indie publishing was
2010 to about
2016. Those numbers can be fudged. uh on
the 16 end during this era the
publishers were not ready for ebooks
yet but indie authors which uh continues
to be kind of a case with indie authors
were faster to move and uh led the
charge was led by a few very big authors
who had been part of New York publishing
whose books kind of had all gone out of
print and they put them all back up so
they had huge backlists uh but also some
indie romance authors who started
publishing uh Amanda Hawking being one
of them. And suddenly there was all
these people had Kindles that they had
bought and all these people wanted books
on their Kindles and the publishers were
slow to put them up and put them up
expensively. Meanwhile, here's this
Amanda Hawking book. It's $ 2.99 and you
can click a button and read it. Gold
Rush era, uh, indie publishing explodes.
an enormous boom of indie publishing and
really good in a lot of ways for the
industry. It does gobble up more of the
mid list, making the New York publishers
more gunshy on mid list. Uh mid list
being those books that sell well enough
to make a profit, but not so much to pay
for anyone else, right? Um best sellers
being the ones that make enough profit
to basically pay your overhead for all
the new experiments you're going to do
and things like that. um like I don't
have the exact numbers um but I remember
looking once and um at tour I was the
number one book of the year um and I had
sold like my my new book had sold like
500,000 copies in hardcover or something
like that um across uh yeah um you're
gasping or you're just yawning. Pretend
you're gasping because that's a really
good number. Pretend that like Diary of
Wimpy Kid doesn't sell like 9 million.
Um
um but tours number two was something
like 20,000 copies that year, right? Um
and the differences between number ones
and number TWs like in the film industry
tend to be a pretty huge gap. Um I think
I'm exaggerating that number a little
bit. I'd have to actually go look at it.
But the number two is not 80% of number
one generally. it is a fraction of it
because that's just how bestellerdom
works. Um and so
um what's going on is your mid list are
getting gobbled up by the indie authors
and the publishers are like why are we
publishing any midlisters? They still do
but they they don't want midlisters
anymore. And this is part of the reason
gold rush era happens. Amazon realizes
these indie authors could be giving them
money and the gold rush ends about 2016.
This is when the publishers finally
figure out how to price their books
correctly, how to do sales on their
books. Kindle also around this time, I
can't remember the exact date, launches
Kindle Unlimited
uh and starts to have an all you can eat
buffet and a lot of the indie authors
gets uh go into that. Um, Kindle
Unlimited when we've experimented with
it has made significantly less money
than not being an unlimited. Um, their
mileage may vary depending on how many
books you write and how many are in
Kindle Unlimited and things like this.
Um, but it comes out, it's a monthly
subscription that takes a lot of the
readers who just want to be able to push
a button and read. Um, and Amazon starts
put charging ads uh to its uh to its
indie authors and publishers in order to
get books placed. And for a little
while, it was really bad. I remember
coming to class one year and holding it
up and we counted the number of ads on a
page for uh the Stormlight Archive and
there was something like 12 advertised
books before you got to anything that
wasn't advertised, including the second
Stormlight book.
um that you could click on to buy. They
have since backed off on this, but for a
little while, Amazon was paytoplay,
meaning you I had friends who were
spending six figures in ad money in
order to make 50 grand. So, they were
like sometimes spending twice as much as
they made just in ads to stay at the uh
recommended enough that they were
getting picked up enough and sold. I
hear it's balanced out a little bit. And
these days, Amazon ads are not as
valuable as they used to be. Um, and
that might just be because Amazon
realized it was creating a bad user
experience. And like we should go back a
little bit to the algorithm of
recommending to people what used to be.
You go on the page and say people who
like this book also like this book. And
then people trusted that bought it and
they were usually right because you know
it was an organic algorithm rather than
pay to put something there. When it
started to be paid to put something
there, people were like, I don't like
this book very much. Um, and then they
stopped trusting those and so Amazon in
the long run makes less money. Uh,
they've balanced that out a little bit
better. But even still today, the gold
rush is kind of over. Doesn't mean you
can't indie publish. People can be very
successful indie publishing. Uh, but
nowadays it is more work. You need to
learn your keywords. You need to learn
how and when to publish, how to do your
promos. And I can't give you all of
that.
You need to go to serious indie authors
who are paying attention to what works
right now because anything I tell you
will be out of
date. The other big disruption happened
in the form excuse me of audiobooks.
Audiobooks back in the day I listened to
the Wheel of Time books checking them
out from the library. There was like 80
cassette
tapes. You're laughing but I think it
was actually 80. Like you got these
giant books. They were like styrofoam.
Any other oldies in here remember these
things? Uh, and you'd have to like punch
out, you know, like pull out uh the
cassette, put it in, and it would go and
then you put it back in. Um, and then
you get out the next one, and you know,
you hope they'd rewind it, but, you
know, you usually just have to rewind it
before you started. And that's how you
listen to the Wheel of Time. Eventually,
they became CD bricks like that um that
you would get that were all so puffy
because they're from libraries and they
know people are going to drop them. Um
and then Audible came along and
disrupted this market by saying, "What
if we instead of selling you a $60 set
of 80 cassette tapes that basically no
one bought? No one really did. Truckers
bought them in
libraries. What if you could buy a
subscription and get one for $15 a
month? any audio book you want and you
just put it on your iPod and you listen
to it or your iPhone and everyone's like
that sounds great. Let's do that. Uh and
while ebooks were starting to lull a
little bit and stabilize, audiobooks
just exploded. Uh when people started
having enough hard drive space basically
to just push a button and download an
audiobook. Um which again you young
people that took a frightening amount of
time. You don't understand. Waiting a
half hour to Napster the theme
song to Beverly Hills Cop, which is like
two minutes long, and then it getting
interrupted halfway through and starting
over. And so you spend 3 hours
downloading one song, and only then do
you find out it's illegal because, oh
yeah, that might be copyright
infringement. Nobody
knew. It was just a fun thing the nerds
did. Um, so
yeah, I'm serious. No one, we're all
doing this. And then when someone said
that might be illegal when when
Metallica is like, "Hey, don't rip our
music off." We're like,
"Oh, yeah. Yeah, you should sell it to
us." And they're like, "It's on CD."
We're like, "No, no, no. You should sell
it to us so we can push the button. We
like pushing the
button." And then they did. Took them a
little while for Metallica to jump on
that one, but they did. Um, so anyway,
audiobooks disrupted the market a great
deal to the point that it's still
today, the only segment of the market
that is a very serious growth segment.
All books tend to do better and better
every year, like everything, but they
kind of just grow with population um,
and things like that. Audiobooks have
been gobbling up ebook and um and print
book audiences, but also gaining new
audiences consistently since kind of the
the boom started. It's a it's tapered
off. Um Stormlight 5, I believe, was
under 20%
print. I think it was 18% print and it
was overwhelmingly audio. It was
something like 50% audio, 30% ebook, 20%
print. Uh for its few first weeks, we
overperform in audio because uh people
have
credits and Stormlight 5 is 60 hours
long. And you can look and see that and
be like one credit 9hour other person's
book one credit 60
hours plus Michael and Kate are awesome
and do just fantastic job with the
narrative narration um and so we do
overperform uh plus sci-fi fantasy does
tend to overperform both in ebook and
audiobook for instance middlegrade still
doesn't sell in either one very well uh
ya it's a crapshoot
um right um whether people are reading
in print or um in ebook audio but sci-fi
fantasy overperforms and I way
overperform um until Michelle Obama uh
released her book I was the top
pre-ordered book in the history of
Audible and then Michelle Obama beat me.
Thanks
Obama. The other Obama but thanks that
was a nice record. I enjoyed that for
for like a
year.
Um,
so let's talk about the parts of a
publishing industry. All right. Any
questions on my brief overly simplistic
history of the publishing industry and
the big disruptions. Now it's run by
what big is it still five? Still five,
right? Is it four? I think it's four.
It's four. No, they were they was going
to go to four, but then they stopped it.
I mean, they still tell us in editing
classes that it's the big five. It's the
big five. Yeah. I mean, my professors
might be out of date, but what's that?
Hashett McMillan.
Harper. Simon, who's the other one?
Warner. No, Penguin. No, did you get
Penguin? Yeah. How can we forget Rand
and Penguin? They're the biggest. So,
there you are. There's your big five.
Uh, the big five gobbled everything up.
Uh, I asked my agent before anything he
thought I should mention to you guys.
Uh, he gave me two points. Uh he said
number one it's good for authors that
the Simon Schustster uh PR um merger
didn't go through just more options are
good for authors. The other one he said
is uh Amazon is scary. Uh and we'll get
into that. Um so questions there was one
back here on my brief overly busy
history of the the
industry. Okay. All right. Let's talk
about where we are right
now. What is traditional publishing?
What's it good for?
Um, right now as things stand, for a
while indie publishing was the place to
be. Now, I would say there are very good
arguments for both.
Unfortunately, indie publishing has
become harder in recent years because ad
spend has become, even if you're not
spending on Amazon, spending it on Tik
Tok or making trying to find ways to
make your books go viral is a decent
chunk of indie publishing. And there are
upfront fees. To do well in indie
publishing, you need to have
professionally edited and professionally
made cover. You can do this cheaper than
I do it, right? Like what do we pay for
a cover? It's like eight grand, right?
Something. Depends on the artist.
Depends on the artist. Yeah. But between
like 25 and 8 2500 and 8 grand depending
on if it's a digital only, if it's a
painting, it's something like this. Um,
you can get very good covers for less
than that. Um, but your cover and your
cover design need to look professional.
Your editing needs to look professional.
Um, and so you do need to spend upfront.
And I would talk to the indie people
about how to do this on the cheap if you
need to do it. Indie publishing, the
only other thing I'll say is name of the
game still tends to be being able to go
viral managed with releasing as many
books as humanly possible. The more
books you have in Indie, the better. Um,
and a lot of people who indie publish
like they'll say we you want a book uh
every six
weeks. Yes, you heard that. weeks. There
are any publisher authors who release a
book every six weeks.
Um that is some of the ones doing the
best. Most of them do not do that. But
still like I even Jansancy when she uh
did a big push, she released one a month
after saving them up for several
years because that's how you make a
splash indie publishing is you have just
you become mildly viral on Kindle
Unlimited. You want people to tear
through your catalog and if you release
one
book and they read it, you get almost
nothing. If they tear through your
catalog, you make a lot more. And so you
have to be able to have people tear
through your catalog. So any publishing
having a a large amount of books does
tend to be the primary way. There are
other ways uh that people do it, but
that's one of the things. All right,
let's talk about a publishing company.
Again, I want you to understand like
we're pretending you want to be a
professional industry. It's good for you
to know the parts of all this. It's a
fire hose. You can come back and watch
this online later.
Um, in a publishing hubry, you have the
publisher. This is someone like Tom
Dherty. A publisher is not an editor. A
publisher is a business person. Their
primary job is to herd
nerds. Okay? Even at the non- nerdy
publisher, non-science fiction
publisher, everybody else is a nerd,
right? This is a business person. Their
background is in business. Their
background is to actually make all these
people who love books and don't care
about numbers pay attention to the
numbers. So that means that while Tom
Dhy generally read one book by each of
his authors, he knew science fiction
fantasy. He loved science fiction
fantasy. You could not sell a book to
Tom
Dherty. Peter Dh Dan and I didn't know
this when we cornered him at World Con
in
2001 and talked to Zir off trying to get
him to buy our books. Uh Tom Dhy can't
buy your books. you're kind of barking
up the wrong tree unless you know your
daughter goes to school with his
granddaughter and he can put in a good
word for you. Like that does still
happen. Right underneath the publisher
is usually um what we call an editorial
director. All right. In some companies
there's an associate publisher instead.
So let's do put right here associate
These jobs can be kind of
interchangeable, right? Uh it depends on
how big the company is and things like
this. Uh a lot of times, so at tour, uh
during the the years when I was there,
Tom had associate publishers, one over
children's and one over like libraries
and all of these things. Um and there
was only an editorial director over tour
itself. Her name was Harriet McDougall,
Robert Jordan's um widow. Uh his first
his editor, then his wife. She uh she
met him, published him, then married
him. Uh I joke it's like she wanted to
make extra sure she listened to her
editorial directive. Um right editorial
director is somebody who has enough
business sense and management
sense to to be a nerd who knows how to
pay attention to the business side
whereas an associate publisher is just a
publisher in you know a VP they they
work and this is why it's kind of you
run the gambit sometimes an often an
editorial director will have their own
line of books whereas associate
publisher won't and that's kind of one
of the distinctions between them. They
will manage a group of
editors that says editors. There's going
to be a certain group of editors at the
company. And these will have various
ranks based on how long they've been
there and how important they want to
sound. But generally, if they're at this
rank, what that means is they acquire
fiction. These are the people who can
buy your
books. They are the people actively
searching for new books and they are
book people first. A lot of them these
days have come up through the editing
programs at the various universities. So
they have had to learn the publisher
side a little bit which is generally
good for everyone. When I broke in, they
were all people who went to all these
cons and just went long enough that
someone said, "You have good taste. Why
don't you start being an editor?" Mosha,
my
editor, he became an editor because he
collect collected issues of Analog, the
science fiction magazine, and he was
missing one. So, he went to the editor's
house, which was there in Manhattan, or
I guess in Queens. uh walked up and
knocked on the door and said, "Hey, do
you have this issue?" And they're like,
"Yeah, I think I have it in the back.
Come on in." And he's like, "Did you
like that issue?" And Mosha talked about
what he liked. And he's like, "Here, sit
down and read some of this slush pile
and tell me what you
think." Mosha read the slush pile and
said, "I like this story, this story,
and this story." They're like, "Those
are the ones I picked. You want a
job?" That is how Mosha entered science
fiction and fantasy. He's like in his
20s.
Um, right. He eventually does that for a
while, gets hired by the science fiction
book club to pick their science fiction
uh things. Tor hires him, makes him an
assistant editor um to David Hartwell um
and he's assistant editor for a few
years and then um I was at a convention
and Jean Cavellis said we asked her,
"Hey, who's acquiring right now?" She
said, "Go look up Mosha Feder. He was
David Hartwell's assistant. They just
promoted him and said he could start
acquiring. He doesn't have a list yet.
He's going to be hungry. And so we found
him at a party, Dan and I. Um, we talked
his ear off. He talked our ear off. We
both sent him books. He bought a launch.
And then a few years later, he bought
one of Dan's books. So that's how we
that's how I broke in, right? Um, we'll
talk about how you break in nowadays. It
doesn't work the same way.
Um,
so an editor's job is to act as a
project manager for a book. This is
something that people outside the
industry do not understand. Okay. They
think that an editor if you go if you're
who anyone here in the editing program
here. Yeah. If you tell people they'll
be like, "Oh, so you look for typos."
I mean, I do because I'm a copy editor.
Okay. You're a copy editor.
Yeah. Um, but that's generally not the
editor's job. They won't be able to help
themselves because they're type of
person, right? But an editor's job, an
editor acquires a book and is project
manager for that book. They oversee the
editing of it, but also they interface
with all the other parts of the company.
So, let's say that your book is in this
stack sent to them by an agent, because
that's basically how it happens. now
sneaking in behind the through the back
door like I did doesn't happen as often
anymore. They read your book in the
stack and they say, "Oh, I want to buy
this." They then will go to whoever's
above them at tour. During my era, it
was actually straight to Tom to the
publisher. Usually, it's the editorial
director or associate publisher or
whoever it is. Like at Random House,
there'll be a publisher that's not of
Random House that's just in charge of a
line. like uh at Delicort where I
published uh my YA books. Uh they had a
publisher um who just retired. She was
wonderful. And her job was basically
just to manage the five editors at that
imprint. An imprint is when these big
publishers gobbled up a small publisher,
they usually liked the name and also the
little publisher generally had like an
editorial style and a good reputation.
So often they would just kind of keep
them as a little subsidiary called an
imprint. Penguin Random House is the
biggest. It has a like dozens of
imprints. Delicort is an imprint of
Penguin Random House. It has a publisher
for Delicort and then a group of editors
at Delicort who all try to find books
that match the Delicort line that have a
similar sort of YA feel to other things
at in Delort. Um, and then that person
uh will Beverly would report to a higher
up publisher who would report then to
the people above the publishers which
are all like the money people at
McMillan and stuff like that that we're
not even going to talk about. These are
like these are like they could be they
could be selling shirts, they could be
selling books, they don't really care
does the line go up, right? Um that's
their job. There's nothing wrong with
that. Um that's why they have a
publisher who cares about books and
knows the industry running the thing. So
they they they get your book and they're
like, "I want to buy this book." They go
to whoever is up there and they say, "I
found one. I think it's really great. We
should buy it." Usually this person will
read it or at least, you know, read part
of it and be like, "Okay, make me a
[Applause]
PNL." A P&L is a profit and loss
statement or sheet.
When I asked Joshua what a P&L was, he
said, 'Oh, it's a bunch of madeup
numbers, and it kind of is. So, what a
P&L is is the p the editor will go and
be like, where what market do I think
this will sell to? What what book will
this sell? Like, uh where where how are
we going to publish this? Will we do it
in hard coverver or straight to
paperback? What's our market for this?
Um, and they will do all the number
crunching stuff that they don't like to
do, but now they have been learned to do
because they all went through the
publishing program. Do they talk about
P&Ls for you guys? Yeah, you do. You're
a copy editor, so you don't have to
worry about it. Um, so the P&L and they
will plug in a bunch of numbers and they
will take this and they'll talk it
through and say, "This is what I think
we can sell." And that will determine
what they can offer on the book as an
advance.
An advance
is an amount of money they pay upfront
to the um to the author in order to buy
the rights to publish the book in
whatever markets they is in the
contract. Um you get this money up
front. You do not have to pay this money
back unless you fail to deliver. So if
you don't earn enough money, you don't
have to pay it back.
Now, this is an advance against your
royalties. So when the book comes out
and sells, you will earn a certain
percent off of cover price for every
copy sold. In the industry right now,
that is generally between 10 and 15% off
of cover price on a hard cover. So if
they whatever the number is on there the
regardless of how it's discounted every
copy that sells you get between 10 and
15%. Usually this uh it escalates you
start at 10% you sell a certain
threshold you start getting 12 a.5 after
uh then a second threshold you get 15%.
That when I broke in it was fairly
standardized at 5,000 first 5,000 copies
got 10%. second 5,000 got he's got 12
and a half and everything over 10,000
copies got 15. Um and so you generally
get between six and
8% sometimes 10% on a mass market little
paperback cover price. You generally get
between 6 and 10% sometimes 12 but
usually around 8 to 10 off of a trade
paperback which is the oversized one.
Yeah. Are those percentages retroactive?
Uh so once you hit that five that 10,000
Nope. It's kind of like the tax code,
right? Does that make sense? Those first
5,000 earn you this much, next 5,000
earn you this much, and then that. It's
not retroactive. Good question. um in
this regard for a long time cuz these uh
contracts were really heavily negotiated
over a century's time they got pretty
standardized and they were relatively
fair I feel to the author uh you might
say
15% that's not a ton but remember retail
is keeping 50%. Okay. So, if we run
these are very rough numbers, okay,
exceptionally rough, but if we run some
numbers and let's pretend that a book
was $10. That's not an actual number,
but it's easy for math. So, a $10 book,
we're giving around $5 to the bookstore,
right? $5 is coming to the publisher.
Um, to print a $10 book, you will expect
about a dollar in printing fees, 10%
printing, and another 10% is warehousing
and shipping and all of that stuff. So,
there's really $3
left. 150 of that, if you're selling
well, goes to the author and 150 of that
goes to the publisher. It's actually a
pretty fair split. Again, only $1 we go
do on the first part part. Part of the
reason for that is um they're going to
pay for cover art and co um copy editing
and all these things that are a sunk
cost. It's a certain amount to make a
book and it doesn't increase like
printing does. If you print more, you
get a cheaper price for printing, but
you still have to pay for every book.
The more copies you print, the more all
of those sunk costs get a million amber
get split among all the pieces. So this
percentage I felt was kind of because we
got two over here. Um that's kind of
like distribution slash all of that.
This is very simple. Those numbers
actually are not as even as I make them
seem, but that was a pretty decent
split. The publishers didn't really like
that that it was so even a split. And
then ebooks came along.
And ebooks generally work under a
different model of
$10. Usually the um the you get 25% of
net. Okay. So net is defined fortunately
not in a Hollywood accounting way as
what the publisher actually takes in. So
usually
30% goes to Amazon. It's going to be
Amazon. Amazon's 90% of the ebook
market. Um, and then of that $10, $7
goes over here. They pay you 25% of
that, right? How much is that? Uh, math
people, how much is 25% of $7? Little
under two. Little under two bucks. We'll
go two
bucks. So, you get $2. You're like,
"Wow, I made 50 cents
extra. We're all doing great." How much
does the publisher make?
$5. How much are they spending in
printing fees? None. None. They took the
money from the printing fees and the
warehousing fees and they just put it
into their pocket which is why everyone
was up in arms that 25% and that became
the industry standard. You should still
be up in arms about that. It has not
changed. Um but it is that is what
happened and that is where the
publishers managed to make a little edge
in the disruption of the market that
came
um it can be
budged. You can do things that will make
them give you more. I can't say because
of contractoral obligations what you can
do to make them
budge but I can tell you Stephen King
did it and I think he talked about it.
So
um but there are there are they can be
creative. You have to be a big deal to
make them be creative. Okay. What they
will tell you is they have contracts in
their their contracts that say they
can't pay you higher than 25% of net
because they pay you higher. They have
to pay everyone higher. They have lots
of authors who have most favored nation
clauses. That is true. Contracts can do
all kinds of things. So, we'll just
leave it there. All
right. So, they will come back to you.
They will offer you an advance. Average
advance um 10 years ago was five grand.
I don't think it's
increased. Um it's not a lot of money,
is it? No. Um, and that's five grand
being pulled up by the people who make
250 grand and things like that. Um, a
good agent should be able to get that
higher than five. Five is pretty low.
Um, but I got 10
uh 20 grand for two books. Basically,
it's what Joshua got me to in 2005. Um,
that is an advance. Every one of those
dollars you earn in royalties will go
against that advance. So, you can run
the numbers. If you were making a $1.50
per book and you got a $10,000 advance,
you could see how many books it would
take you to sell before you start
getting a royalty check.
Okay. Any questions on that before we
start talking about how artwork happens,
how editing happens, uh, and and all of
that in distribution?
Yeah. Is there anything that like we as
consumers other than just being super
vocal about it can be more up in arms
about it to like push for change? What
can you do to push for change? This is a
good question. And I my uh Joshua
actually said the number one thing you
can do for put to bush for change is
actually buy your ebooks from places
other than Amazon right now because this
honestly I don't like this but this is
on the authors and the agents to change
not on the the consumer right you can
support indie authors uh if you like
indie authors but I don't think you
shouldn't support traditionally
published authors they still want you to
buy their books even though this uh the
way that ebooks have gone is unfair
making videos like I'm doing here and
saying, "Hey, publishers, you were fine
with a $150 before. What changed? Why
isn't this a better a better split? You
know how bad this looks. You should be
ashamed of yourself. They really just
should be, right? Um, you know, the p
the industry did really well uh
splitting evenly with the authors. Um
and
so yeah uh we can do that but uh the
bigger problem is Amazon. So Amazon
dominating the market to the level they
do is bad for everybody. Not a lot we
can do. Uh the publishers had some a
snafu with them um back in 2011 2012 or
whatever that ended up with a department
of justice judgment against the
publishers um for things they had done.
and Amazon came out very well in that
exchange. Um, and the publishers are
very gunshy against uh going against
Amazon right now. It's hard because most
of the people who work at Amazon are
great bookloving nerds just like the
rest of us who just want to work in
publishing. They have no power to change
this. Uh, and the people who do have
power to change this are the equivalents
at Amazon above this person. And they
just say, "Yes, but the number is going
up." Uh, and that's what we want it to
do. And you know uh the problem with
them controlling the market is they just
for instance for indie authors they can
just say now you have to kind of pay us
a bunch of money in order to advertise
in order to sell. Indie author authoring
no longer makes the better margins once
in a while the reason to do this is
indie authoring you got to keep the $7.
So even if you sold half as many books
indie publishing guess what you're
beating the two bucks. So why wouldn't
you? Well, now you have to spend a bunch
of that money on
ads and so because you do your royalties
and also Amazon has a little behind
the-scenes extra fee they charge uh to
indie authors. It's not very big for
most, but they charge a distribution fee
to them and not to publishers. Uh if you
don't have art in your book, it's not
significant, but for the Way of Kings,
we calculated be it would have been like
about 70 cents a book because of the
artwork we put in it. Um, and so if in
Way of Kings were indie published, uh,
we would be losing an additional 70
cents or something like that. Peter
knows the actual numbers. Um, and so
there's there's all these things going
on with Amazon being able to squeeze
they, for instance, they allow the
publishers, Joshua brought this up, they
allow the publishers to set any price
for their ebooks they want. Indie
authors have to keep them under 10
bucks, and that's the same price now as
it was in 2010.
Indie authors haven't been able to raise
prices on their books since two 2010.
Um, and that means that if you have a
book that is three times as long as
someone else's, you can't charge $12
compared to their $9 book. Even though
it's three times as long and has all
this artwork that they're charging you.7
cents for, you still have to charge
$9.99. It's your maximum. 2.99 is your
minimum. There are things like this that
just make it hard for the indie authors
um and things like that. So real change
is going to require number one that to
happen but number two um something to
happen where the authors are able to
force uh the publishers to bend on this
25% of net. Um and you know audiobooks
are still kind of highway robbery for
the same reason. Uh we talk about this
but it's actually different over here.
Um Audible isn't paying $3 off of the
the 10. Um they're paying a fraction of
that. I think they're paying like 30% to
the author instead of
70%. Um, and we got them to change some
of that, but they haven't still haven't
even rolled that out yet. Uh, and it's a
marginal increase. It's not an enormous
increase. So, we'll see when they
finally do roll that out. Uh, what
Dragon Steel's efforts have managed to
do there to get them to bend a little
bit. Uh, but basically all the tech bro
industry people have said, everyone's so
eager to publish books and they're
really easy to take advantage of. So,
let's just take advantage of them. Um,
whereas, you know, uh, in video
games, they know they can't get away
with it. So, they they give them the
higher royalties and things. So, that's
not part of this discussion. I can't
really get into that. Let's just kind of
go through. You get your advance, you
get your royalties. We talked about what
the royalties are. By the way, on
audiobooks, it's also generally uh 25%
of net. Yeah. Can you negotiate a lower
advance or not having an advance to get
a higher royalty?
You can't. Maybe someday you
can. Uh, basically you will have to be
able to threaten to walk away from all
of the big five publishers and be able
to do it on your own and cost them
significant amounts of off their bottom
line before they will agree to a deal
like that because if they do they know
that that is opening that
floodgate and that is bad for them. This
has been very good for them because
while um while u the India book market
has gobbled up the mid list, they've
been able to focus on bestsellers and
make this percentage off the majority of
the best seller instead of this
percentage. Uh and so it's been how the
publishing industry has kind of
survived, right? But you know it's at
the expense of authors. So, um, so your
book gets picked up at that point.
Again, editor's project manager. What
they're going to do is they're going to
send you an editorial
letter. This is a long letter of here's
everything wrong with your book. If
you're in YA, it'll also tell you the
good things about your book.
I'm joking, but it is kind of a stark
difference uh working in YA and middle
grade with those editors where they'll
be like, "Oh, I love this smiley face
here. Oh, blah blah blah blah blah."
Whereas working with uh with New York
editors where like Mosha once said to
me, he said, "This sucks. You didn't
used to suck. What went wrong?"
and Harriet once circled a page uh in
the Wheel of Time, crossed it out and
wrote do
better. Where over at Delicort they're
like oh smiley face heart heart there's
like hearts on half the pages. Um yeah.
Yeah. Difference between YA and adult.
Um or at least the publishers I've
worked at. Um New Yorkers. Yeah. They're
just New Yorkers, right? Like uh what's
that? Mine was nicer. Yours was nicer.
Yeah. You you didn't yours yours. Yeah.
It might also be that Christa Delicort,
she's from LA. People smile a lot in LA.
Mosha is a died in the wool New Yorker.
He is as New Yorker as you can get.
Right. And like the when I after we
signed and I met him and I went back,
he's like, "When did you get so
fat?" I'm like he's like, "I don't
remember you being this fat. You have to
live a long time to make me a lot of
money, lose
weight.
Anyone who's known New Yorkers was like,
"Yeah, okay." That he was being really
nice, wasn't he?
Yeah, he kind of was. Um, he was he did
it endearingly and he wore all Yankees.
He wears Yankee stuff everywhere. Um,
just straight up, you know, you won't
ever catch him without his Yankees
jacket on. Um, so they then will
editorial letter, they'll work with you.
Um, I'm making it sound worse than it
is. I've had a wonderful experience with
basically every editor I've worked with.
Their job is to help you make a better
version of the book you want to write.
They are not trying to turn it into
anything you don't want it to be. They
work with you. They talk it over. They
uh once you've signed the contracts, the
editor is your friend. Uh during
contract negotiations, they're the
enemy. Every other time, they are your
friend. They want the book to succeed.
They will be your in-house advocate.
they will start going to marketing
meetings because over here you have P
and M publicity and marketing
uh defined a little differently I found
depending on the place but in general
marketing is where they spend money on
ads of any sort and publicity is where
they go direct to the fans doing some
sort of publicity of uh event like
publicity sponsors uh your book tours
They they help you with your Tik Toks.
They, you know, do things like this.
Marketing goes and buys ads in
newspapers, which they really shouldn't
do. They don't do that much anymore, but
buys ads on Amazon, buys ads on Tik Tok,
right? The the difference being they're
you know, publicity is kind of like not
I don't know you maybe you can kind of
see the difference there. Uh, but post
publicity, your publicist will generally
handle getting you on talk shows, which
you'll never get on. Um, George got on
on on one um on Col Bear. I was on Col
Bear. My face was on Co
Bear. Uh, back during the day of the Col
Bear Report, he had a rant he made about
Zeppelins and he held up a copy of USA
Today. There was an article about me on
the bottom of
it. So, I've got a screenshot of my face
on the Co Bear
Report. Um, but uh Shannon Hail got on
uh Good Morning America. This sort of
stuff authors don't go on and it's not
that big a deal anyway anymore. So, um
but they will they know how to do the
whole Tik Tok thing and stuff like that.
So, um one of the cur curious things to
know about that's part of marketing is
what we call co-op. If you walk into a
bookstore, anything but the actual
shelves is paid
for. Okay? If when you walk into your
Barnes & Noble, there's those nice
displays of books that say summer reads
or something, that's paid space. If you
look behind the register and there's a
wall of books saying new awesome book
here, that's paid for space. Most of the
end caps are paid for space. That's at
the end of a thing. Um, this is all what
we call co-op. And when I say paid for,
it's not paid for in this way you might
think. It's paid for in that they will
say, "Hey, Barnes & Noble's like, "Hey,
we got space on this Zen cap cap. If we
put yours there and we sell it, can we
have an extra 50 cents?" And the
publisher will be like, "Yeah, sure."
Um, and that comes out of their $150,
not yours. So, you really like it when
that happens. When it happens over here,
it comes out of both of yours because
it's net. Um, so once again, it's one
something they changed for the ebooks.
When Amazon comes and says, "Hey, we got
a promo. You sell your book at $5 and we
will put it a part of our newsletter."
Usually co-op for Amazon is less than
getting a bigger percentage and more
bringing your price down or something
like that to do a value. Sometimes it is
getting a a percent or something like
that, but usually it's this. Then you uh
you split that uh with the the
publisher. You you both take the hit.
So, yay for progress.
Um, so,
uh, if they don't ask and discount it,
then it doesn't come out of either of
yours. Uh, this is rarely relevant, but
it happened to me once. Do you guys
remember, any of you old enough to
remember when everyone got mad that they
put, uh, YouTube's new album on
everyone's iPhone? They also put The Way
of Kings on everyone's
iPhone, but Bono's a bigger target, so
nobody noticed me.
They just did it and then they paid us
for them all. I made like 800
grand. Yeah, it was enormous.
Uh yeah. Uh-huh. They just did it. It's
just Apple. They're like, "Well,
whatever." They We heard that people
like The Way of Kings. You can have it
for free if you buy a new iPhone. People
bought new iPhones. They put the Way of
Kings on it and they sent me a check. I
sent to a check who sent me a check. It
was really great. We loved it. But
yeah. Yeah. If they'd asked us, we would
have been like, "Yeah, give it out for
free." Then we would have got nothing.
But they this Apple, they just didn't
ask. They just did it, you know.
I'll take your money.
Um, so, uh, so yeah, publicity
marketing, they'll be talking to them.
They'll be talking to the in-house
accountants and all this stuff. The
accounting people will handle the
contracts. Your agent will negotiate
that with them. We'll talk agents next
week. Um because as I assumed we weren't
going to get there because we got to
Hey, contracts, royalties, retail. Um so
contracts, you will be offered a
contract and your agent will negotiate
it. We'll talk in depth about what those
are, but you eventually when you talk
royalties will go to retail. Uh they
will ship them all to the bookstores out
in the world and the bookstores can
return them. And so you won't get paid
until after they know how many books are
getting returned. This can be very
frustrating. They keep what's called a
reserve against returns. Uh where they
are like well we these books could come
back at any time. Basically they get to
keep your money and earn interest on it
a little longer worrying that there
might be returns and your agent might
yell at them and say we have the book
scan numbers which are like the Neielson
ratings. We know that they sold you have
to send us money. the publisher will be
like all right fine and then they'll
send you the money. Um okay you
understand the publishing industry kind
of now this is how the industry works
editors acquire they love books they
then get everyone in house excited when
a launch got published was giving it to
the the accountants he was giving to
everybody getting them all excited for
the book you get everybody hyped
publishing marketing gets involved they
will hopefully do some publishing
marketing book tour buy and co-op are
the main two ways that they would do
that then the book comes out and then
you hope that people buy it. And we'll
talk next week about how hard that is to
get people to do in today's market for a
new um authors. All right, we got five
minutes for questions. Any questions? Uh
so you talked about like audio books
kind of shook things up and ebooks. Is
there anything coming up that is there
anything coming up to shake up
publishing? We don't know. Um, for a
while I was worried that the big shakeup
would be driving books uh prices down
further. Uh, which is why I moved into
uh into premium editions as Dragon
Steel's primary business model right
now. Um, and I feel like I preaged
something because a lot of people
followed
um, premium editions after we started
our big our dragon steel editions. um
premium editions became the thing and I
think uh think Al Crate and Loot Crate
and Fairy Crate and all of those. Um
this was back, you know, I I started
this in like 2011 2012 uh building the
um the additions with our first one
coming out in 2014
um I think uh or 2015
um and premium editions. So what
happens? Why premium editions? Well, I
have this philosophy that that you can
still make money as an artist if the
more wellto-do of your fans subsidize
everyone else who gets the uh the thing
for cheap or free. It's basically the
model that the music industry has used
for a long time. You have the premium uh
concert experience. Everybody else can
listen to the the music basically for
free. Uh royalties are crap in music and
even before then there was the radio.
Uh, and so I was like, if books are
going to go to 99 cents, I need to have
something to subsidize that. Uh, and
that's why we built Dragon Steel. Uh,
keeping your premium edition rights,
therefore is something I would highly
recommend.
They She says they won't let you. Your
your editor might be able to make them.
Yeah, it's because of all the books. All
the book crates are they're very much
harder. So, I started keeping my audio
book rights and then the publishers
realized they shouldn't do that. and
everybody else has had trouble keeping
their audiobook rights. I kept my uh my
um my premium rights and now it's hard
for every I'm sorry to do this to you
all. Um basically whatever I end up
doing the publishers won't let anyone
else do. Um but uh try to do whatever it
is you see Dragon Steel doing. Uh yeah,
I was just wondering when you're
pitching your book idea to like a
publisher, what can you do to make
yourself stand out? like what are they
looking for in a novel? What are they
looking for in a novel makes you stand
out?
Um, if you have a pitch session, I
recommend
um Boy, we should talk about pitching
next week. Yeah, let's Well, I'll have
Rachel remind me. We'll talk about
pitching next week. Next week. Because
that'll go into query letters as well.
Okay. Yeah. As far as audio books go,
how expensive on average is it for an
indie author to get an audio book? uh
audio book. Getting an audio book made
um it's about for top tier talent is
about 10 grand for a uh for one of our
um secret projects. So not the super
long books cheaper. You can get it
cheaper than that, but you're looking
two to three grand I think for quality
talent that's not uh the top tier names.
Uh am I right on that? Do you're Yeah,
that's right. That's Peter's department,
not your department. So I think two to
three grand. Um, if you want to use
professionals and not
amateurs. Okay. Uh, yeah, it's by
finished hour, by the way. They you'll
find how much they charge by finished
hour. Uh, does anyone have a is it like
300 bucks per finished hour sometimes?
Something like that. Yeah, 300 bucks per
finished hour. 250 bucks per finished
hour. 10 hours is a is a an average
shorter book. So, uh, yeah. Over here.
Have you ever been pressured by a
publisher to include or exclude any
content? Have I been pub pressured by
publisher to include or exclude content?
Never. I've never heard of it happening
to anyone I know um in science fiction
fantasy. It might be different in
romance. People wonder that a lot. Never
happened to me in my entire life. It
happens in it's happened on the Wheel of
Time movies or television show because
they wanted a Game of Thrones. But in
publishing, this is basically a
non-issue. Uh never even heard of it.
Yeah. Uh over here. Do you feel like the
narrators with the big names like draw
people? Do I think narrators the big
names draw people? Yes. I like the nar
really good narrators, but your mileage
may vary. I don't know if you go get
Michael and Kate and you pay the extra
money if it's going to be worth the
value to you until you already have a
fan base. Uh save your questions, write
them down. We'll have a whole Q&A
episode, the last episode. Thank you all
very much. Um appreciate I know
[Applause]